-==www.RagBear.com==- 福尔摩斯探案集  第1季第7集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=- 校对: ptrpan
这里是莫卡伯爵夫人家 谢谢
Countess of Morcar's, thanks.
天呐 她回来了
My God, she's back.
她下马车了
She's getting out of the carriage.
快 赖德 赶紧的
Come on, Ryder, get a move on.
修好了吧
...look lively.
好了
All right.
动作快点      快点
Get moving.        All right.
伯爵夫人讨厌看到管子工在她家晃悠
Her ladyship won't want workmen under her feet.
好了 别担心 我修好了
All right, I finished, don't worry,
听你的 我可加紧速度干活
quick job, like you said.
真是美奂绝伦啊
Oh, yeah, yeah, nice, nice.
伯爵夫人的 嗯?
Countess, eh?
也就约会时戴戴...
Have to get by appointment only...
走吧 伙计
Come on, lad, out.
可以走了
All right.
放一边就行了
Over there will do.
给你们仨的
Here, for the three of you.
谢谢 夫人
Thank you, milady,
祝您圣诞快乐
and a Merry Christmas, milady.
给我叫杯茶 丘萨克
Ring for tea, Cusack.
好的 夫人
Yes, milady.
我得喝杯茶 提提神
I need something to sustain me.
圣诞前夕的准备工作真是折磨人
I do find preparing for Christmas quite an ordeal.
您说得对 夫人
Yes, milady.
之后 再洗个澡
And then, a bath, I think.
夫人
Milady.
蓝宝石
The blue carbuncle,
蓝宝石 被偷了
the blue carbuncle, it's stolen.
把眼睛睁开 看
Open them up, there.
噢 约翰 她会喜欢的 这太美了
Oh, John, she'll love it, it is beautiful.
就像她的妈妈
Just like her mother.
可我们买得起吗?
But can we afford it, though?
我告诉过你 我最近赚了点小钱
I told you, I made a nice little bob or two lately.
即使没钱 现在可是圣诞节
Even if I hadn't, it's Christmas.
你真体贴 约翰・霍纳
You're a good man, John Horner.
我真幸运
I'm a lucky man,
妻儿在旁
a wife and kids like I've got,
快活似神仙
means as good as a king.
那买这洋娃娃给女儿
So, it's the doll for the girl,
这船送咱的儿子 你说如何?
and the boat for the boy, right?
就这样吧
Right.
迫不及待销赃了 霍纳?
Spending the loot already, are we, Horner?
什么意思?
What do you mean?
我什么都没做 你什么意思?
I've done nothing, what do you mean?
约翰・弗雷德里克・霍纳
John Frederick Horner,
你因盗窃莫卡伯爵夫人
I hereby arrest you on the charge of stealing
名下价值连城的
the valuable gem known as the blue carbuncle,
蓝宝石而被捕了
the property of the Countess of Morcar.
你所说的...
Anything you say...
我没偷 我真的没偷
I didn't do it, I tell you, I didn't do it.
有人看到你 旅馆里的人
A man saw you. The man at the hotel
口里描述的就是你
gave a very good description of you.
治安官        不是我偷的 相信我
Constable.        I didn't do it, I tell you,
放我走 真的不是我偷的
let me go, will you, I didn't do it.
噢
Oh.
福尔摩斯先生?
Mr. Holmes?
彼得森先生 阿伯赛特的看门人...
Mr. Peterson, the commissionaire from Upasit...
他有事找你      别来烦我
...he'd like a word with you.        Oh, please, go away.
噢
Oh.
福尔摩斯先生 抱歉打扰您了
I'm sorry to disturb you, Mr. Holmes.
彼得森 把鹅放下
Peterson, put down your goose,
还有你的帽子
and your, your hat.
你买了只肥鹅
It's a fine purchase,
我就很喜欢圣诞大餐吃肥鹅
I myself favor a goose for Christmas dinner.
可问题也出在这 福尔摩斯先生
Well, that's part of the problem, Mr. Holmes.
这鹅不是我的
the bird is not mine.
您也许会说 是我弄来的
You might say, I come by it.
"献给亨利・贝克太太"
Oh, "for Mrs. Henry Baker,"
显然 这不是你的帽子
and obviously, not your hat.
当然不是 先生
No, sir.
情况特殊
Well, there were peculiar circumstances,
我不知道该如何处理
and I didn't know what to do for the best.
报警有点太小题大作
It hardly seemed a matter for the police.
我便和我太太说了这事
So I talked to the wife about it,
她建议我来找您
and she suggested I come and see you.
你太太很聪明
The wise Mrs. Peterson.
坐下吧 我亲爱的朋友
Sit down, my dear fellow,
把特殊情况给我讲讲
and describe these peculiar circumstances to me.
好的 是这样的
Well, sir, it was like this.
昨晚我在归家途中 我刚参加完一个
Last night I was on my way home from a little,
小小的聚会
uh, celebration.
每年的这个时候
Well, at this time of the year
我们几个看门人凑在一起...
some of us commissionairs meet to -
交换下节日祝福      没错
To wish each other the season's greetings.        Exactly.
节日祝福
The season's greetings.
您真厉害 先生
Oh, you're a top, sir.
敬你的健康
Your good health, sir.
正如我之前说的 我在归家途中
Well, as I was saying, I was on my way home
遇到了意外事件
when I came across what you would only describe as a frakel.
喂 你们在干吗?
Oy, what's happening?
嘿 是警察...
Blimey, it's a copper,...
大家快逃 快逃啊
Get out of here. Get out of here.
快逃
Get out of here.
我是在帮你啊 老兄
I'm trying to help you, man.
流氓都往一个方向跑了
Well, the roughs ran off in one direction,
醉鬼也往相反方向溜了
and the drunk fellow ran off in the other.
我想叫住他 但他显然以为
I tried to stop him, but he no doubt thought
我是个治安官 打算
I was a constable about to apprehend him
以打破玻璃罪逮捕他
for the breaking of the window.
所以你就掳获了两样战利品
And so you left with the spoils of victory
这顶破旧的毡帽
in the shape of that battered hat,
和一只上等的圣诞肥鹅
and a most unimpeachable Christmas goose.
我迫切希望将它们
Both of which I would willingly
物归原主 福尔摩斯先生
have returned to their rightful owners, Mr. Holmes,
可我不知道该从何下手
but the truth is, I didn't know how.
亲爱的彼得森 我明白你的困境了
My dear Peterson, I do see your problem.
不管怎样 我说了
Anyway, as I say,
我和太太商量过
I discussed the matter with the good lady,
决定把这两样东西
and we decided that I would bring both
帽子和鹅带到您这 福尔摩斯先生
the goose and the hat to you, Mr. Holmes,
不知道这件小事能否引起
seeing as how even the slightest of problems is of interest
你这一特殊行业人士的兴趣
to you in your particular line of occupation.
但愿我没浪费您的时间 福尔摩斯先生
I hope you don't think I'm wasting your time, Mr. Holmes.
当然没有
Not in the least.
好了 看门人
Now then, Commissionaire,
你自家的鹅买好了吗?      还没呢
have you purchased your own bird?        No, not yet.
那我建议你把这只鹅带回家
Then I suggest that you carry off this goose
去完成它的最终命运
so that it may fulfill its ultimate destiny,
而我就好好保存失去了圣诞大餐
while I retain the battered hat of the unknown gentleman
的素未谋面的先生的破旧毡帽
who has lost his Christmas dinner.
就听你的 福尔摩斯先生
Well, if you think I should, Mr. Holmes.
那就这样吧
I do, indeed.
尽管天气寒冷 但有迹象表明
For there are signs, in spite of the frost,
该吃掉它了
that this bird should be prepared
没必要再放着了
without unnecessary delay.
那我就不客气了 福尔摩斯先生
Well, if that's all right, Mr. Holmes.
一有进展
I will of course,
我就联系你
keep you in touch with the developments.
好的 先生
Very good, sir.
呃 祝您节日快乐
Oh, uh, may I wish you the complements of the season.
也祝你和你的太太
And to you and your good wife.
你们还是没找到宝石
But you still haven't found the jewel.
是还没 夫人
Not yet, no, milady,
但我们抓到小偷了 就是霍纳
but we do have the man, Horner.
那宝石的线索呢
Or have a clue as to its whereabouts.
我们推断
And I think we may assume
他有帮凶 也许不止一个
that he had one accomplice, if not more.
什么意思?
Well, what of that?
夫人 和小说的情节恰恰相反
Contrary to popular fiction, milady,
小偷都没什么信誉
there is very little honor amongst thieves,
一看到钱就把信誉抛之脑后
and even less with the right inducement.
钱 你是指悬赏?
Inducement, do you mean a reward?
呃 没错
Uh, yes.
我为什么要提供赏金?
Why should I offer a reward?
以我的经验 这是相当有效的
In my experience, and it is considerable,
我发现悬赏
I have found that the offer of a reward
能把那个贪婪的小偷给引出来
would very soon set the greedy cat amongst the criminal pigeon.
是吗?
Well?
如果24小时内
I should be very surprised
没人来领赏 那才叫奇怪呢
if I did not gain a result within 24 hours.
那悬赏多少?
How much?
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
噢 你在啊
Oh, you're up.
莫卡伯爵夫人悬赏1千英镑
The Countess of Morcar is offering a thousand pounds
寻找蓝宝石的下落
for the return of the blue carbuncle.
B区布雷兹特里特巡官
Inspector Bradstreet of B Division
负责此案
is in charge of the case,
他已经逮捕了约翰・霍纳
and has arrested Mr. John Horner,
36岁 是个水管工
a plumber, age 36,
强烈申辩自己是无辜的
who protested his innocence in the strongest terms.
由于间接证据确凿
Circumstantial evidence was so strong that the case
此案已移交给巡回审判庭
has been referred to the Assizes.
霍纳在诉讼中情绪激动
Horner, who showed signs of intense emotion
做最后陈述时竟昏了过去
during the proceedings, faded away at the conclusion
被抬出了法庭
and was carried from the court.
抱歉 你正忙着呢
Oh, excuse me, you are engaged.
打扰到你研究帽子了
I am interrupting your study of that hat.
不 这完全是件毫无价值的东西
No, no, no, the matter is a perfectly trivial one.
但与它有关的几个问题
But there are points in connection with it
却不是那么无聊
which are not devoid of interest,
甚至还有教益
even of instruction.
我想 这顶帽子看似普通
I suppose that homely as it looks,
实则关系到某件性命攸关的事
that thing has some deadly story linked to it that
就是这条线索能帮你解开某个疑团
is the clue which will guide you in the solution of some mystery
警恶惩奸
and the punishment of some crime.
不不不不
No, no, no, no,
这只是众多离奇小事中的一件罢了
it is just one of those whimsical little instance
400万人口挤在几平方英里的
that will occur when you have four million people
弹丸之地 这种事少不了
jostling each other within the space of a few square miles.
那你从这顶破毡帽上瞧出了什么?
So, what do you gather from that battered old felt?
你素来明白我的方法
You know my methods.
对戴这么特别的毡帽的人的个性
What do you yourself gather as to the individuality
你推测出什么来了吗?
of the man who has worn this particular article?
它是连同一只肥鹅送过来的 华生
It was accompanied by a goose, Watson.
肥鹅的左腿上系着张小卡片 写着
"For Mrs. Henry Baker," was printed upon a small card
"献给亨利・贝克夫人"
attached to the bird's left leg.
除了这缩写
Well, apart from the initials inside,
H.B. 假设是指"亨利・贝克"
H.B., presumably Henry Baker...
我看不出其他啥信息
...I can see nothing.
恰恰相反 华生 你什么都能看出来
On the contrary, Watson, you can see everything,
但你没有就所看到的东西作出推论
but you fail to reason for what you see.
你对自己的推论能力太缺乏信心了
You are too timid in drawing your inferences.
那么
Then, pray,
你告诉我你从这帽子上作出了啥推论?
tell me what it is that you can infer from that hat?
这是个学识渊博的人
That the man is highly intellectual
这一眼就能看出
is, of course, obvious.
而且在过去三年里
And also that he was fairly well-to-do
生活相当富裕
within the past three years,
虽然他目前穷困潦倒
although now he has fallen upon evil days.
他过去很有远见 如今已大不如前
He had foresight, but less now than formerly,
精神日渐颓废
pointing to a moral retrogression,
加上家道中落
which, when taken with the decline of his fortunes,
他应该染上了恶习 也许是酗酒吧
seems to indicate an evil influence, probably drink.
恐怕这也是他妻子
This may account also for the fact that his wife
不再爱他的原因
has ceased to love him.
我亲爱的福尔摩斯
My dear, Holmes.
但他仍保有最后的自尊
He has, however, retained some degree of self-respect,
他深居简出
and now he leads a sedentary life,
完全缺乏锻炼
is out of training entirely.
是个中年人 头发灰白
He's middle-aged, has grizzled hair
最近几天刚理过发
which he has had cut within the last few days,
头发上还抹了柠檬膏
and which he anoints with lime-cream.
而且他家里绝不可能
It is also highly improbable that he has gas
有煤油灯
laid on in his house.
你肯定在开玩笑
Well, now you are certainly joking.
根本不是玩笑
Not in the least.
我不怀疑我很迟钝
Well, I have no doubt that I am very stupid.
比方说 你怎么推出他学识渊博?
For example, how do you deduce that the man is intellectual?
这是一个容积的问题
It is a question of cubic capacity.
脑袋那么大的人 脑子里肯定有不少货
A man with so large a head must have something in it.
那家道中落呢?
Well, the decline in his fortunes, then?
这种平沿卷边帽
These flat brims with the curled edges
在三年前很流行
came in three years ago.
华生 这是顶质量上乘的帽子
It is a hat of the very best quality, Watson.
瞧瞧这丝绸的箍带和华贵的衬里
Look at the band of ribbed silk and the excellent lining.
如果他三年前买得起这么贵的帽子
If this man could afford so expensive a hat
而以后再没添置过新帽子
three years ago, and has had no hat since,
那么显然他失势潦倒了
then he has assuredly gone down in the world.
他过去有远见如今精神颓废又怎样?
What about the foresight and the moral retrogression?
这就说明他有远见
Ah, here is the foresight,
出售的帽子是不附带松紧带的
these securers are never sold upon hats.
所以这是他订做的
If this man ordered one,
这恰好说明他有远见
it is a sign of a certain amount of foresight,
他用这种方法
since he went out of his way
防止帽子被风刮跑
to take precaution against the wind.
但你看 他把松紧带坏了
But as you see that he has broken the elastic
却不愿花点时间重新订一条
and has not troubled to replace it,
说明他意志消沉
a weakening nature.
嗯
Mmm.
此外还有几点 他是个中年人
The further points, that he is middle-aged,
头发灰白 最近刚理过发
that his hair is grizzled, that it has been cut recently,
头上抹过柠檬膏
and that he anoints it with lime-cream,
这些都可以从帽子衬里
can all to be gathered by an inspection
下部的检查中推断出来
of the lower part of the lining, Watson.
看这的湿迹 显然 他出汗量很大
Witness the moisture, obviously a free perspirer,
所以不是一个勤于锻炼的人
therefore, not in the best of training.
那他...他的妻子
But his - his wife,
他刚说她不再爱他了
you said she had ceased to love him.
这帽子几周没刷过了
This hat has not been brushed for weeks.
如果我看到一个男人的帽子
When I see a man
已经积了个把星期的灰尘
with a week's accumulation of dust upon his hat,
而他的妻子却置之不理
and his wife has allowed him to go out in such a state,
我恐怕他已很不幸地
I fear that he has been unfortunate enough
失去他妻子的爱了
to lose his wife's affections.
他也许是单身汉啊
He might be a bachelor.
不是 他想将鹅作为示好礼物送他妻子
Nay, but he brought a goose as a peace offering to his wife.
别忘了系在鹅腿上的那张卡片
Remember the card attached to the bird's leg.
你总是能找到答案
Yes, well, you have an answer to everything.
慢着
Just a minute, just a minute,
你怎么推断出他家没有煤油灯?
how do you deduce that there is no gas laid on in his house?
一滴烛油
One tallow candle stain,
或两滴烛油 也许是偶然滴到
or even two, might come by chance;
可是 华生 当我看到有不只5滴时
but when I see, Watson, no less than five,
就知道他不可能从煤油灯上沾到烛油
he never got candle stains from a gas jet, Watson.
满意了吗?
Are you satisfied?
你脑子真灵
Well, it's all very ingenious.
那只鹅 福尔摩斯先生 那只鹅
Mr. Holmes, the goose, the goose, Mr. Holmes.
怎么啦 难道它又活了?
Well, what of it, man, has it come back to life
扑拉着翅膀从厨房的窗口飞出去了?
and flapped off through the kitchen window?
不 先生 你瞧
No, no sir, no sir, but see,
我妻子在嗉囊里发现了什么
see what the wife found in its crop.
天呐 彼得森 这确实是件秘藏的珍宝
By Jove, Peterson, this is a treasure-trove indeed.
你知道这是什么吗?
You know what you've got?
一颗钻石 一颗宝石
A diamond, a precious stone.
用它割玻璃像割油泥一样
It cuts glass like it was putty.
这不是一颗平常的宝石
It is more than a precious stone.
而是那颗名贵的宝石
It is the precious stone.
世界旅馆盗窃案
The Hotel Cosmopolitan robbery,
那颗蓝宝石
the blue carbuncle.
千真万确
The blue carbuncle, indeed.
这绝对是独一无二的珍宝
It is absolutely unique,
它的价值只能大约估计
its value can only be conjectured.
而悬赏的1000英镑报酬
And your reward, Peterson,
还不到这颗蓝宝石
of 1000 pounds is not within a twentieth
市价的1/20
of its market price.
1000英镑 老天爷呀
A thousand pounds, oh, Lord have mercy.
你得承认 华生
You must admit, Watson,
我从帽子上推断出来的信息
that my deductions in regard to this hat
其重要性可是陡然大增
have suddenly assumed a more important aspect.
那是 福尔摩斯
Yes, point taken, Holmes.
我们现在要解决的问题是
Now, the question for us now to solve is to trace
理清从宝石被盗到发现鹅的嗦囊
the sequence of events from a rifled jewel case at one end,
这期间一系列事件的顺序
to the crop of a goose at the other.
这就是那颗宝石
There is the stone.
那颗宝石来自那只鹅
The stone came from the goose,
那只鹅来自亨利・贝克先生
the goose came from Mr. Henry Baker,
他戴着顶破毡帽
the gentleman with the shabby hat
还有其他特征
and all the other characteristics.
我们现在要做的是
So, now, we must set ourselves very seriously
认真找到这位先生
to finding this gentleman,
并且弄清他在这起神秘事件中
and to ascertaining what part he had to play
扮演何种角色
in this little mystery.
兹于古治街拐角
Found at the corner of Goodge Street,
拣到鹅一只和黑毡帽一顶
a goose and a black felt hat.
亨利・贝克先生请于晚六点半
Mr. Henry Baker can have same by applying at 6:30 this evening
到贝克街221B房领回 简单又明了
at 221B, Baker Street, clear and concise.
没错 可他会看到吗?
Yes, very, but will he see it?
当然 他肯定会留意晚报
Well, I'm sure he will keep an eye on the evening papers,
对穷人来说 这损失也算惨重了
for the poor man, the loss was a heavy one.
彼得森 把它送到广告公司
Oh, Peterson, uh, just nip down to the advertising agency
并且刊登在所有的晚报上
and have this put in all the evening papers.
登在哪家报纸上 先生?
Which, one, sir?
《环球报》《星报》《蓓尔美尔报》《圣詹姆斯宫报》
The Globe, Star, Pall Mall, St. James's Bissett,
《回声报》《新闻晚报》《标准报》
Echo,Evening News, Standard,
和所有你得想到的报纸
and all the others that may occur to you.
这就去办 先生
Right away, sir.
那宝石怎么办?
And the stone?
这颗宝石我先保存着
I shall keep the stone.
谢谢你 彼得森
Thank you, Peterson.
举手之劳 先生
Yes, sir.
还有 彼得森
Oh, and Peterson,
你回来的路上能帮我买只鹅吗?
uh, would you pick up a goose on your way back?
把钱给他 华生
Give him the money, will you, Watson.
我必须给亨利・贝克先生买一只鹅
We must have something to give Mr. Henry Baker
来代替
to take the place of the one
你们全家要享用的那只
which your family will very soon be devouring.
好的 谢谢你 先生
Oh, thank you, sir.
1000英镑?
A thousand pounds?
1000英镑
A thousand pounds.
1000英镑 1000英镑
A thousand pounds, a thousand pounds.
你打算怎么处理这颗宝石?
Um, what, uh, will you do with the stone?
我要把它放进我的陈列柜
I shall keep it in my museum.
霍纳
Well, Horner,
伯爵夫人对我很生气
Her Ladyship is not at all pleased with me.
你虽然被关了起来
You might be under lock and key,
但她更关心宝石的下落
but she'd rather her blue carbuncle was.
我从没拿过宝石 治安官
Never took it Inspector...
这...
Well -
你把它藏哪了 说
Tell me what you did with it, and, uh,
也许我可以帮你向法官求情
I'll put in a good word at your trial.
但如果你不识相
But, if you don't -
自从我娶了杰瑞
I've been on the straight for years,
我就一直安分守己
ever since I married Jenny.
如果你不说实话
If you don't,
当法官得知了你的前科
and when the judge hears about your previous conviction,
恐怕你再也见不到你的娇妻了
you might never see your pretty wife again.
我抓到你了 霍纳 但我更需要宝石
I've got you, Horner, but I need that jewel.
真是颗美仑美奂的宝石
It's a bonny thing,
你看啊 多么光彩照人
just see how it glints and sparkles.
当然 它又是罪恶的根源
Of course, it is a nucleus and focus of crime,
每颗珍贵的宝石无不如此
every good stone is.
它们是魔鬼得意的诱饵
They are the devil's pet baits.
在更大更古老的宝石上
In the larger and older jewels
每一个切割面都代表着残忍的罪行
every facet may stand for a bloody deed.
它是在华南厦门的河边被发现的
It was found in the banks of the Amoy River in southern China,
它的奇特之处在于 除了它是蓝的
and is remarkable in having every characteristic of the carbuncle,
它拥有红宝石的一切特征
save that it is blue instead of ruby red.
这颗宝石问世以来不到20年
This stone is not yet twenty years old.
尽管流传在世不久
In spite of its youth,
但已有一段不堪的历史
it already has a sinister history.
两起谋杀案
There have been two murders,
一起硫酸毁容案 一起自杀事件
a vitriol-throwing, a suicide,
还有几起抢劫案都归因于
and several robberies brought about for the sake
这颗重四十谷的结晶碳
of this forty-grain weight of crystallized charcoal.
谁会想到如此美的饰物竟是
Who would think that so pretty a toy
向绞刑架和监狱输送罪犯的供应商呢?
could be a purveyor to the gallows and the prison?
进来
Come in.
你就是亨利・贝克先生吧?
Mr. Henry Baker, I believe?
请坐近壁炉
Please, draw near the fire.
今天真冷啊 我想你的血液循环
It is a cold night and I observe that your circulation
在夏天一定比在冬天强
is more adapted for summer than for winter.
快坐下吧
Do sit down.
这是我的好友兼搭档 华生医生
This is my friend and colleague, Dr. Watson.
你好 先生
How do you do, sir?
贝克先生
Mr. Baker...
这是你的帽子吗?
is that your hat?
是的 这的确是我的帽子
Oh, yes, oh, it is undoubtedly my hat.
谢谢你 先生
Thank you, sir.
我想登寻物启事
I would have advertised its loss but shillings
可我已囊中羞涩 大不如前了
have not been so plentiful with me as they once were.
我以为那些袭击我的流氓
I had no doubt that the gang of roughs
抢走了帽子和鹅
who assaulted me had carried off both my hat and the bird.
我想没有必要为拿不回的东西
I did not care to spend more money
再多花钱了
in a hopeless attempt at recovering them.
当然 这我能理解
Yes, well, of course, that is very understandable.
对了 你的那只鹅
Oh, by the way, about your bird,
我们不得已把它给吃掉了
we were compelled to eat it.
吃掉了
To eat it.
如果不这么做 那鹅就真的不堪食用了
It would have been of little use to anyone had we not done so.
但我们又买了一只鹅 就在餐柜上
But we have another goose upon the sideboard there,
我想它和你那只鹅应该差不多
which I presume will answer your purpose equally well.
重量不相上下
It is about the same weight,
而且十分鲜嫩
and perfectly fresh, as you can see.
噢 那当然了
Oh, yes, most certainly.
当然 我们还留着原来那只鹅的
Of course, we have kept the feathers, legs, crop,
羽毛 腿 嗉囊等等 如果你想要
and so on of your own bird, if you so wish.
作为我的历险纪念品也许有点用处
It might be useful to me as relics of my adventure,
除此之外
but beyond that I can hardly see
我看不出我那鹅的零星碎物
what use the disjectamembra of my old acquaintance
对我有何用处
could possibly be to me.
如果你不介意
Oh, no, sir, with your permission,
我...我想我关心的是
I - I shall confine my attentions
我在你餐柜上看到的那只肥鹅
to the excellent bird which I perceive upon your sideboard.
我想知道
I would be interested to know
你那只鹅是在哪买的
where the other bird came from.
我对饲养家禽很有兴趣
You see, I am somewhat of a fowl fancier,
我很少见到如此好的肥鹅
and I have seldom seen a better grown bird.
所以我对你买下鹅
It would be of great interest to me to know
的细节极有兴趣
precisely how it came into your possession.
是俱乐部给我的 先生 一个鹅俱乐部
It was the club, sir, the goose club.
鹅俱乐部? 说得再具体点
The goose club, the exact circumstances?
我...我不是个富人
I - I am not a rich man,
正如你看到的 先生 我的生活窘迫
as you may see, sir, but I make a humble living,
但也不失尊严 这样说吧
and a respectable one, if I may say so,
我在大英博物馆工作
in the British Museum.
做研究?
Studying?
算是吧
Studying, you might say,
也帮助别人做研究
and helping others with their studies.
我看过很多书
I - I have a certain knowledge of books.
那天 我提早下班
That day, sir, I had finished work early
下午就离开了博物馆
and left the museum in the afternoon.
我办完私事
I had a little business to attend to
就去了阿尔法小酒店
before calling in at the Alpha Public House.
博物馆的好些同事
Several of us who work in the museum
经常去那儿
frequent that establishment,
今年 我们的好店主
and this year our good host,
温迪盖特先生 创办了一个鹅俱乐部
Mr. Windigate, had instigated a goose club,
考虑到每周向俱乐部交纳几便士
by which, on consideration of some few pence each week,
我们在圣诞节都收到一只鹅
we were to receive a bird at Christmas.
给你的 贝克先生
There we are, Mr. Baker,
说好的 一只上等肥鹅
a very fine bird, as promised.
真是难得一见的肥鹅 老板
Magnificent specimen, indeed, landlord, eh.
这下能和你妻子重修旧好了吧?
Put you back in the wife's good books, eh?
恐怕她对我还是有点不满
Well, she is still somewhat irked with me, I'm afraid.
等我又找到能赚钱的工作时
Things may doubtless improve when I am
一切肯定会有好转
once more in gainful employment.
噢 肯定是学术性的工作
Oh, an academic nature, of course.
我很有前途的
Yeah I have expectations.
这是上次欠你的8便士
Well, I owe you one last payment of eight pennies, eh.
"一夜暴富"了 贝克先生?
Struck it rich, have we, Mr. B?
我碰巧遇到一个
I chanced upon an acquaintance
富有同情心的熟人 其实呢
of sympathetic disposition, I, that is to say,
我卖给他几本我的书
I sold some of my books.
不是你的书吧 贝克先生
Oh, not your books, Mr. Baker.
这也是迫不得已 温迪盖特先生
Needs must, Mr. Windigate,
今年的冬天比以往更窘迫
and at this season of the year more than ever,
我们不能割舍所爱之物
we must not deprive those we love,
所娶之人更应好好珍惜
or even those to whom we are married.
先把这份示好礼物放一边
And so, if you will set aside this impressive peace offering,
我得缓解下压力
I shall fortify myself for the fray
所以给我来一大杯威士忌
with a large glass of whiskey,
再来一品脱你这最好的啤酒
and a pint of your most excellent beer.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas to you.
圣诞快乐 贝克先生
Same to you, Mr. Baker.
在我回家的路上
Well, sir, on my way home
我被一群流氓袭击
I was attacked by the gang of roughs,
我以为他们偷了我的鹅
who I believed had stolen the goose.
我的帽子也在扭打中丢了
My hat came off in the scuffle.
我...我就记得
I - I remember little of it,
一个穿制服的警官出现在现场
save that a uniformed officer appeared on the scene
于是我们都逃走了
and we all made off.
这是当然 我们能理解
Yes, of course, we quite understand.
在那种情况下嘛
In the circumstances.
结果好 才是真的好
Well, all is well that ends well.
我对您的费心深表谢意 先生
I am most indebted to you, sir, for your trouble.
我想这顶苏格兰帽
A scottish bonnet, I fear,
既不符合我的年龄 也不符合我的身份
is fitted neither to my years nor to my dignity.
节日快乐 先生
My complements of the season to you, sir.
你也是啊 先生
And to you, too, sir.
谢谢你
Oh, thank you, sir.
噢 对了
Oh, uh, by the way,
你家有煤油灯吗?
do you have gas laid on in your house?
煤油灯 当然没有
Gas, alas, no.
很好
Jolly good.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas.
也祝您俩圣诞快乐
And to you both, gentlemen.
好了 亨利・贝克先生的事到此结束
Well then, so much for Mr. Henry Baker.
他显然对宝石的事一无所知
He obviously knows nothing of the matter.
哈德森太太
Ah, Mrs. Hudson.
华生 你饿吗?
Watson, do you need nourishment?
不是很饿
Not particularly.
太好了
Splendid.
哈德森太太 把我们的晚餐改成夜宵吧
Mrs. Hudson, we shall turn dinner into supper,
我们要顺藤摸瓜 趁热打铁
and we will follow up this clue while it is still hot.
能比夜宵还热么?
Which is more than the supper will be.
晚上好 先生们 今晚真是冷啊
Good evening, gentlemen, and a very cold one.
确实是啊 老板
It is, indeed, landlord, it is indeed.
你们想喝什么?
And what shall be your pleasure?
啤酒 华生?
Beer, Watson?
什么? 噢 好的
What? Oh, yes, splendid.
来两杯你这最好的啤酒
Two of your very best glasses of beer.
稍等 先生
Right away, sir.
如果你的啤酒和你的鹅一样好
Your beer should be excellent
那就是最纯正的啤酒了
if it is as good as your geese.
我的鹅?
What geese?
半小时前 我们刚和
Yes. We were talking, um, half an hour ago
你鹅俱乐部的会员亨利・贝克先生聊过
to a Mr. Henry Baker, a member of your goose club.
这样啊 可那些鹅不是我们的
Yes, but you see, them's not our geese.
那是谁的?
Whose, then?
我从考文特园一个商贩那
Well, I got the whole two dozen
买了24只
from a salesman in Covent Garden.
他叫什么名字?
Who might that be?
布莱肯里奇
Name of Breckinridge,
一个供货商 他那总有好货
a purveyor of the finest quality.
提醒你 如果你想买只鹅
Mind you, if it's a bird you're after,
我可以立马去找他
I'd get to him as soon as poss.
你们也知道 现在正是
Oh, it's a very busy time of year,
一年中最忙的时候
as you'll appreciate.
谢谢你的建议
Well, thank you so much for your advice.
能再来杯啤酒吗?
Will you have a glass of beer with us, landlord?
上帝保佑你 先生
Well, God bless you for a gentleman.
现在就去找布莱肯里奇
Now, for Mr. Breckinridge.
非得现在去?
Can't it wait?
华生 我们正在追踪一条
Watson, we have been given a line of investigation
被警察忽略了的线索
which has been missed by the police,
这条线索机缘巧合落入了我们手中
and which a singular chance has placed in our hands.
我们得顺着线索不惜一切 追查到底
Now, let us follow it out to the bitter end.
真是不惜一切啊
Extremely bitter.
现在朝南快步前进
Faces to the south, then, and quick, march.
别哭了
Please.
我也想相信你 约翰 真的
I want to believe you, John, I do, really,
可我没法反驳警察说的话
but I can't argue with what the police is saying.
但他们只说抓我是因为当天我在那里
But they're only saying that cause I was there on the day.
我只是去做零工
It was an odd job.
真的是这样吗?
Is that really the truth?
结婚时 我答应过你
I promised when I married you,
我永不会对你撒谎
I'd never tell you a lie.
我一直遵守我的诺言
I kept my promise, always will.
我也想相信你
I want to believe you.
晚上好
Uh, good evening.
Good evening.
看来你的鹅都卖光了
Sold out of geese, I see.
没错 明早我可以卖你500只
Yeah, I'll have five hundred in the morning.
太晚了
Too late, I think.
煤油灯亮着的那个摊位上还有
See the stall over there with the gas fire, try him.
但人家介绍我到你这儿来
Yes, but I was recommended to you.
谁?
Oh, who by?
阿尔法小酒店的老板
The landlord of the Alpha Public House.
对 他从我这买了24只
Oh, yeah, he had a couple of dozen off me.
那些鹅真不错
Very good geese, too.
我能知道你是从哪弄来的吗?
Where, may I ask, did you get them?
好吧 先生
Here then, mister,
你到底什么意思?
what exactly are you driving at?
有话直说
Come on, let's have it straight, now.
我已经说得很明白
It's straight enough.
我只想知道你卖给阿尔法店的那些鹅
I simply want to know who sold you the geese
是谁供货的
that you supplied to the Alpha.
我不想告诉你 就是这样
Well then, I'm not gonna tell you, so now.
这只是件小事 可我不明白
It really is of no matter, but I fail to see
你为何如此大动肝火
why you should get so warm over a trifle.
大动肝火 你试试被这样纠缠看看
Warm, you'd be as warm if you were as pestered as I am.
我花大价钱买好货
When I pay good money for a good article
这不就完事了吗?
that should be an end of it;
什么 "鹅在哪"
but it's where are the geese,
"你把鹅卖给谁了"
who have you sold them to,
"卖了多少价钱"
how much will you take for them?
好像对这批鹅过分关心
You would think those were the only geese in the world,
就能觉得世上没别的鹅了
the amount of fuss that's made over them.
我保证我和其余来查问的人
Well, I can assure you that I have no connection
没有任何关系
with anybody else who's made inquiries.
查问? 这简直就是审问
Inquiries, it's more like the inquisition.
我不会告诉你的
I'm not telling you.
那打赌只好吹了
Ah, well then, the bet is off.
打什么赌?
What bet?
我永远坚持
Well, I'm always ready to back my opinion
我在家禽问题上的看法
on the matter of fowls,
我和我这位朋友赌5英镑
and I have a fiver with my friend here
说我选的那只鹅是在农村喂大的 对吧?
that the bird that I chose is country bred, right, Watson?
什么? 对对对 有这么回事
What? Oh, oh, oh, yes, yes, absolutely.
那你输了 因为它是在城里喂大的
Ah, you've lost your money then, cause it's town bred.
才不是这样
It is nothing of the kind.
就是这样
I say it is.
我不信
I don't believe you.
钱拿来吧 福尔摩斯
Come on, pay up, Holmes.
你以为我不懂
What, do you think I wouldn't know,
我可是从小就和家禽打交道
me, who's been handling fowl since I was a nipper?
我告诉你吧
I'll tell you,
卖给阿尔法店的鹅全是城里喂大的
all the birds that went to the Alpha were town bred.
你说服不了我
You'll never make me believe that.
拜托 福尔摩斯 愿赌服输
Come on, come on, do the decent, Holmes.
那么你愿意打赌吗?
Will you have a bet, then?
那只是让你输钱罢了
I'll be just taking your money,
但我仍愿意拿一金镑和你赌
but I'll have a sovereign with you,
就是为了教训你的固执己见
just to teach you not to be obstinate.
成交
Done.
那好
Right.
仔细看看 傲慢先生
Now then, Mr. Cocksure,
这就是我的帐本
you see these here books here, well,
上面记录了卖鹅给我的人的名单
this is a list of all the folk what I buy off.
这一页上的都是乡下人
Now, on this page is all me country folk,
这页用红墨水写的都是城里的供货人
and these on this side in red ink are all me town suppliers.
把第三个人的名字给我念出来
Now you read out that third name down to me.
奥克肖特太太 布里克斯顿路117号
Mrs. Oakshott, 117 Brixton Road.
客户号码249
Yeah, account number 249.
很好 你再看一下总帐
Go on, then, turn it up in the ledger.
奥克肖特太太 鸡蛋和家禽供应商?
Mrs. Oakshott, egg and poultry supplier?
那最后记的那笔帐是什么?
Now, what's the last entry?
24只鹅 收价7先令6便士
Twenty-four geese at seven and six pence,
卖给阿尔法小酒店 温迪盖特
sold to Mr. Windigate of the Alpha Public House.
你还有什么话可说吗?
So, what are you gonna say now?
这位先生的5英镑呢?
What about this gentleman's fiver?
干得漂亮 福尔摩斯
Well done, Holmes.
今晚就去见奥克肖特太太吗?
Shall we see this Mrs. Oakshott tonight?
怎么又是你 你烦不烦啊
Oh, no, not you again, I've had enough of you.
我都说了 全卖光了
Listen, I've told you before, clear off.
你听我说 有两只灰冠鹅
But the thing is, there were two gray-headed geese.
听着 我被你和你的鹅烦透了
Now, listen, I've had enough of you and those geese.
你们都见鬼去吧
I wish you was all at the devil together.
如果你再用这些蠢话来烦我
If you come pestering me any more with your silly talk
我就放狗咬你
I'll set the dog on you.
听我说 奥克肖特太太告诉我...
Now, look here, Mrs. Oakshott told me -
你把奥克肖特太太带来 我会给她答复
You bring Mrs. Oakshott here, and I'll answer her,
可这与你何干?
but what have you got to do with it, eh?
我的鹅是从你那买的吗?
Did I buy the geese off you?
没有 可那里面有只鹅是我的
No; but one of them was mine all the same.
那你去找奥克肖特太太要
Well, you go and ask Mrs. Oakshott for it.
她让我来找你
She told me to ask you.
你可以去问普鲁士国王要 反正与我无关
You can ask the King of Prusia, for all I care.
我受够了
I've had enough of this.
快给我滚吧
Go on, get out of it.
省下我们去布里克斯顿的路了
This may save us a trip to Brixton.
抱歉 我刚才无意中
Excuse me, but I could not help overhearing
听到你和那个商贩的谈话
the conversation you had just now with that salesman.
我想这件事我也许能帮到你
I think I can be of assistance to you in this matter.
是吗 你是谁?
Yea, who are you?
我是歇洛克・福尔摩斯
My name is Sherlock Holmes.
我的工作就是知道别人不知道的事
It is my business to know what other people don't know.
可你不可能知道这件事
But you could know nothing of this.
相反 我知道得一清二楚
On the contrary, I know everything of it.
我知道你想寻找
I know that you are trying to find out
布里克斯顿路的奥克肖特太太
the whereabouts of some geese sold by Mrs. Oakshott,
卖给布莱肯里奇某批鹅的下落
of Brixton Road, to our friend, Mr. Breckinridge, over there.
而布莱肯里奇又将鹅卖给了
Who in turn, sold them to Mr. Windigate,
阿尔法小酒店的温迪盖特先生
of the Alpha Public House.
先生 你就是我要找的人
Sir, you're the very man I have longed to meet.
我无法表达我对此事有多大的兴趣
I can hardly explain to you my interest in the matter.
那我建议还是在个更舒服的地方
Then I suggest that we carry on this conversation
讨论此事吧
in rather more comfort.
马车
Cab.
进来 坐吧
Come in, take my chair.
我去换拖鞋
I will just put on my slippers.
我想我们得先知道我们有幸
I think we should know the name of the gentleman
为之效劳的人是谁 对吧 华生?
whom we have the pleasure of assisting, don't you, Watson?
约翰・鲁宾逊
John Robinson.
不不不
Oh, no, no, no, no;
我是问你的真名
your real name.
办正事用化名总不方便
It is so awkward doing business with an alias.
那好吧
Well then, uh,
我的真名是赖德 詹姆斯・赖德
my real name is Ryder, James Ryder.
好的 赖德先生
Yes, Mr. Ryder,
世界旅馆的领班
upper attendant at the Hotel Cosmopolitan.
对
Yes.
你应该很想知道那些鹅
And I suppose you would like to know what happened
的下落 尤其是其中一只
to these geese, or, rather, one goose, in particular,
就是那只白体灰冠的吧?
white, with a gray head?
噢 先生 你能告诉我它的下落吗?
Oh, sir, can you tell me where it went to?
它来过我这
It came here.
你这?
Here?
可惜的是 它已经不在了
Sadly, it is no longer here.
但这只鹅死后下了一个蛋
But it laid an egg after it was dead -
我所见过的最美丽最闪亮的蓝色小蛋
the bonniest, brightest little blue egg you have ever seen.
来 来 我给你看
Come, come, I have it.
游戏结束了 赖德
The game is up, Ryder.
站稳了 当心跌进壁炉里
Bear up, man, you'll be in the fire.
这可怜虫的确很瘦小
And what a wretched little shrimp it is, to be sure,
他再没勇气去犯重罪了
there's enough blood in him for felony.
我已经基本掌握了案件的所有环节
I have almost every link in the chain, Ryder,
你也没什么好告诉我的了
you need tell me very little.
是凯瑟琳・丘萨克唆使我的
Catherine Cusack put me up to it.
她是伯爵夫人的女仆
Her Ladyship's maid.
没错
Exactly.
你从小道消息得知霍纳
You knew from local gossip that Horner
曾经有类似的盗窃行为
had been concerned in some such matter before.
然后你都干了些什么
So what did you do,
你和你的同伙丘萨克在伯爵夫人
you made some small job in milady's room,
的房间里动了点手脚
you and your confederate Cusack.
你设法把霍纳叫去
You then managed that Horner should be sent for.
而你偷了宝石 还报了警
But you, you stole the jewel, then you raised the alarm
不幸的霍纳锒铛入狱
and had this unfortunate man arrested.
看在上帝的份上 可怜可怜我吧
For God's sake, Mr. Holmes, have mercy.
想想我的爸爸 我的妈妈
Think of my father, think of my mother,
他们会伤心欲绝的
it would break their hearts.
我以前从没干过坏事
I mean, I never went wrong before,
我以后再也不敢了 我可以手按圣经发誓
I never will again. I swear it on a Bible.
别把我送去法庭 福尔摩斯先生
Oh, don't - don't bring me to court, Mr. Holmes.
看在上帝的份上 千万别这么做
For God's sake, don't do that to me.
坐回椅子上
Get back into your chair.
现在倒知道跪地求饶了
It is very well to cringe and crawl now,
那你怎么不可怜可怜
but you thought little of the man that you sent
毫不知情却因你而上被告席的霍纳?
to the dock for a crime of which he knew nothing.
我会远走高飞 福尔摩斯先生
I'll fly, Mr. Holmes.
我会离开这个国家
I'll leave the country.
那么对他的指控也就撤销了
Then the charge against him will break down.
这点待会再谈
We'll talk about that later.
现在告诉我 宝石是怎么跑进鹅的肚子里
Now tell me, how came the stone into the goose,
而鹅又怎么会被拿去市场卖的?
and how came the goose into the open market?
告诉我真相
Tell me the truth, now,
这是你保命的唯一希望
for that is your only hope of safety.
我把发生的一切都告诉你
I'll tell it to you just as it happened.
我想最好是带着宝石
I thought it was best to get away with the stone
立即逃走
as quick as I could,
因为我不知道警察何时会想起
for I didn't know at what moment the police might not take it
去搜查我和我的房间
into their heads to search me and my room.
旅馆里没有一个安全的地方
There was nowhere in the hotel where it would be safe.
我假装受人差遣走出旅馆
So, I went out, as if on some commission,
然后去姐姐家想再作打算
and made for my sister's house to think things over.
怎么了 杰姆 你看上去糟透了
Why, Jim, whatever is it, you look terrible.
我受了点惊吓 麦琪
I had a bit of a turn, Maggie.
旅馆里发生了盗窃案
There's been a robbery at the hotel.
你快进屋
You'd better come in.
我走进她饲养鹅的后院
I went into the back yard where she kept the geese,
抽着烟 琢磨着该怎么做
smoked a pipe, and wondered what it would be best to do.
我记得在没想好暂时把石头
I remember that my stomach wasn't gonna stop
藏于何处之前
feeling like a bag of ferrets
我一直心慌意乱
till I found somewhere to hide the stone for a while,
突然 我看见鹅
when suddenly, I looked at the geese,
挤在院子角落里咕咕乱叫
which was hissing and huddling in the corner of the yard.
我姐姐曾告诉我 我可以
My sister had told me that I might have the pick
挑一只鹅作为圣诞礼物
of her geese for a Christmas present.
我挑了一只鹅
I picked out one of the birds,
有灰冠的一只上好肥鹅
a fine thick one with a gray head.
我把宝石塞进它喉咙里
I pushed the stone down its throat
一直塞到手指能够达到的地方
as far as my finger could reach.
我以为所有的麻烦都解决了 这时...
Then I thought all my troubles was over, when...
你抱着那鹅干嘛呢 杰姆?
Whatever are you doing with that bird, Jim?
你说过我可以挑一只当圣诞礼物
Uh, you said I could have one for Christmas,
我在试摸哪一只最肥
so I was just feeling which is the fattest.
我们早把你那只留出来了
We already set yours aside -
我们管它叫"杰姆的鹅"
Jim's bird, we call it.
呃 麦琪 反正哪只对你都一样
Uh, if it's all the same to you, Maggie,
我想要我刚才手上抓着的那只
I'd rather have that one I was handling just now.
可给你留着的那只还要重3磅呢
Well, that one is a good three pounds heavier,
我们可是特地喂肥的
we fattened it up expressly.
没关系
Never mind.
我就要那只 我现在就拿走啦
I'll take the other, and I'll take it now.
随便你
Just as you like.
你要的是哪一只?
Which one is it?
就是中间有灰冠的那只
It's that gray-headed one in the middle.
好吧
Oh, very well.
把它宰了 然后带走吧
Kill it and take it with you.
我照她说的做了 福尔摩斯先生
I did what she said, Mr. Holmes,
我带着鹅去了我朋友家 我们用刀
and I carried the bird to my pal, we got a knife,
将鹅开膛 我的心一下子凉了半截
and we opened it up, my heart turned to water,
嗉囊里根本没有蓝宝石
there was no sign of the stone,
我知道肯定出岔子了
and I knew some terrible mistake must have occurred.
那些鹅都去哪了?
Where have they all gone?
卖给商贩子了啊
To the dealer's.
哪个商贩?
Which dealer's?
考文特园的布莱肯里奇
Breckinridge, of Covent Garden.
告诉我
Tell me, just tell me,
是不是还有一只鹅也是灰冠的?
was there another one which had a gray head?
是啊 一共两只
That's right, two,
连我都分不清它们俩
I could never tell them apart, I couldn't.
怎么了 你怎么那么慌张?
Well, what's the matter, what's all the hurry?
我竭尽全力飞奔到
I ran as hard as my feet would carry me
布莱肯里奇那
to this man Breckinridge;
可他已经把鹅卖光了
but he had sold the lot, and not one word
还不肯告诉我都卖给谁
would he tell me as to where they had gone.
我快疯了
I've gone mad.
现在我已经打上"小偷"的烙印了
And now I'm a branded thief,
尽管我没有得到
without ever having touched the wealth
我为此出卖人格的财宝
for which I've sold my character.
上帝宽恕我吧 上帝宽恕我吧
God help me. God help me.
滚出去
Get out.
什么?
What?
愿上帝保佑你 先生
Heavens, bless you, sir.
给我闭嘴
No more words.
滚吧
Get out.
我得承认 福尔摩斯
I must confess, Holmes,
这有点出乎我的意料
to being a little surprised.
我还没被请到警局告诉他们所不知道的
I am not retained by the police to supply their deficiencies.
也许我也犯了重罪 但我也可能救了某人
Maybe I am committing a felony, but I may be saving a soul.
如果把他送进监狱 那他终身都是囚犯
Send him to jail now, you make him a jailbird for life.
毕竟 现在正是大赦时节 来
Listen, after all, it is the season for forgiveness, come.
半夜了
Midnight.
圣诞快乐 福尔摩斯
Merry Christmas, Holmes.
圣诞快乐 我亲爱的朋友
And to you, my dear friend.
等等
Just a minute.
福尔摩斯 约翰・霍纳还被关押着
Holmes, I cannot contemplate eating
一想到此事我就没法安心吃饭
while John Horner is still on remand.
你想 布雷兹特里或者他的同事
Do you suppose that Bradstreet or one of his colleagues
也许还在苦苦查案呢?
might still be at their desks?
你说得对 华生 我们走
He will. You're quite right, Watson, come, let's go.
破烂熊字幕组 -==www.RagBear.com==- 欢迎加入